Hello.
Welcome everyone.
Today we'll be learning about how kernel
programming actually escaped the kernel
So my name is Anais Dodis Georgiou, and
I'm a developer advocate for Groundcover.
I've been a developer advocate
for about eight, nine years.
And for those of you who don't know
what a developer advocate is, it's
someone who represents the company
to the community and vice versa.
So I make a lot of educational
materials to help users understand
what Groundcover can do, and I also
give feedback back to product so
that they have all the information
they need to make their roadmap.
Today, we're gonna be talking about
kernel technology, specifically eBPF,
which is Extended Berkeley Packet Filter,
and it lets you write k-kernel code
dynamically and outside the kernel.
So I actually first came across
this technology about last
year when I joined Groundcover.
And it's been pretty interesting
to learn about especially within
the context of Groundcover, which
is an observability platform.
And it's built with eBPF.
So that's what eBPF is, and today I wanna
talk to you about the technology so that
we can better understand how Groundcover
works, but more importantly, how…
so that we can better understand
why we should know about
eBPF and why it's important.
Because honestly, it kinda works like
black magic for observability and for a
lot of other things, networking, security.
But a good black magic, though.
It's just incredible when you are
able to s- spin up an eBPF sensor and
immediately get observability data and
telemetry from your application without
any code changes or SDK implementation.
So I wanna share now that kinda eBPF
really… Also, I'm not trying to say
it's a replacement for OTel, a-as an aside
and that they're really complementary
but that you should definitely look
into eBF-eBPF, and hopefully, by the
end of this presentation, you're more
convinced about how cool eBPF is, and
more about its history, et cetera.
So for the agenda for today, what I
wanna start with is talking a bit about
what it is and where it came from to
give that background, and I'll share
some common use cases in the industry
and why it's so good at what it is.
And then I'll go into a more
technical part about how it works.
This is also the coolest part and fairly
short, so I won't go into a ton of detail.
And then finally, we'll end
with a scripting section.
I also wanna take a second
to thank Ori Shuchman.
He's a founding engineer at Groundcover,
and he's actually the author of
this talk and the examples in it.
So all I'm really doing is
sharing his work, and I just wanna
credit him properly for that.
So let's start off.
First things first, what is
eBPF and where did it come from?
So eBPF, we know what it stands for.
We know that it runs in the kernel.
So what exactly is a kernel?
The kernel is the core computer program
inside an operating system, and it acts
as a direct bridge between your computer
software and its physical hardware.
So broadly speaking, it provides the
inter-infrastructure for applications,
the user mode programs that we all write.
And you don't need to know it deeply,
but I just wanted to share the
definition so we're all on the same page.
And the vast majority of software
engineers write application code like
web apps, mobile apps, et cetera, and
that lives entirely inside user mode.
Only special engineers, like
operating system developers
or device driver developers,
actually will work in kernel mode.
And if I write a user mode
application code, that code uses
a lot of things in the kernel.
It uses CPU runtime, it uses memory, all
kinds of devices, reading or writing over
the network, reading a disk, a lot more.
So the main difference
between the two is authority.
Kernel mode has unrestricted access
to the entire system hardware and
memory, while user mode operates with
restricted privileges to protect the OS
from cratchets… crashes, excuse me.
So what is this?
Why am I showing JavaScript code here?
I thought when we were talking about
the kernel, so what's the point?
It's because teaching through comparison
is, A, a good way to learn, and so
what we can see here is that we have
a button defined in HTML at the top,
and below we have an event listener
in JavaScript that defines what
happens when you click the button.
So it's pretty simple.
There's a static HTML code and
a definition of what happens,
and then you might ask, "How
do I handle a certain event?"
Now, in parallel to eBPF, in eBPF,
we define the same sort of event
listener, but it's on the kernel.
So the function at the top, TCP
receiving message, is a kernel
function that's called every time
a packet arrives and before it
reaches our process in user mode.
And below it, I have an eBPF
event listener that every time
a packet arrives, prints the ID
of the process that received it.
So hopefully you're with me so far.
So back to this comparison.
People like to say that eBPF is to
the kernel what JavaScript is to HTML.
It's a well-known and common phrase and
we can credit Brendan Gregg here, but it's
said to appear in a lot of places and from
a lot of people as well So I wanna talk a
little bit about the history as well, and
I really recommend reading the following.
It's called eBPF Documentary: eBPF's
Creation Story and Unlocking the Kernel.
It's an account by Thomas Graf,
who's the CTO at Cisco about the
story of eBPF which originally
started around two thousand eleven.
And basically, eBPF essentially
adds programmability to the kernel,
and it makes the kernel dynamic.
If you try to imagine HTML without
JavaScript, you get a page with some
static thing in it that doesn't respond
at all to how we behave, and that's
the power that eBPF adds to the kernel.
And more and more uses keep appearing that
take advantage of this programmability,
just like when JavaScript started
and peoples began to understand what
the Internet would look like today.
So let's talk about how it all began.
So first we had the world of before
eBPF rather, and in user spaces
changing behavior would be cheap.
You could edit, you could deploy,
you… and then it's live, and if
it crashes and your process dies,
then something else restarts it.
But the kernel works nothing like
that, and so you had two options.
You had to either get a patch
merged upstream or ship an
out-of-tree kernel module.
The upstream option meant review cycles
and a kernel release distro picking it
up, users upgrading, et cetera, and that
was like two to four years before that
change would actually run on your machine.
And then kernel modules ran immediately
with no isolation at all, and you have
full privileges, no process boundaries.
However, a bad pointer panics the
whole machine, not just your service.
So from the perspective of anyone
building it or on it the kernel was frozen
But now some pressure made this, this
conflict kind of untenable around 2011.
And that's really when data centers
vis-virtualized, and everything
started moving to the cloud.
And so we encountered this bottleneck,
and the bottleneck was that there was
application code that we as developers
were writing was no longer actually
a bottleneck because I have tons of
applications running on the same server.
And instead, the issue becomes
the ingress and egress of the
serter-server or the egress and ingress
of the data center, and that's something
that suddenly had to be dealt with.
Physical hosts stopped running
apps and started running packets
between fleets of VMs, and software
networking slack-stack, and the kernel
became load-bearing infrastructure.
Meanwhile, everyone else was
running Linux in production
and wanted it to stop changing.
So we have this issue, just to
highlight this conflict between
stability and velocity, and the
kernel really had no way to give both.
And so this guy, Alexey known today
as the father of eBPF, comes along,
and he s-kind of says the following.
He says, "Load balancing and packet
filtering and all these logics that
run on incoming and outgoing packets,
which are now the bottleneck, they need
to actually run inside the kernel."
And why?
Because previously, these logics ran
from user mode, and packets that came in
would go out to user mode, and something
decided what to do with them, that
they'd come back to the kernel, and then
they could be received by the process
that was supposed to receive them.
And so if we move them to the
kernel, then we'll save a lot.
So yeah, he basically says, "Let's
write a new instruction set." And the
instruction set, for those who are
unfamiliar, is essentially code for
how to talk to the process-processor.
It's like Intel's x86
or Arm or many others.
And he says, "Let's write a new one,
but not actually build a new processor.
Instead, let's write this code, and
the kernel will execute it virtually."
And the reason why this route gets
interesting is because it started
with a networking incident that led
him to an uncomfortable conclusion,
which is that you can't fully trust
the compiler to admit what you meant.
And so you don't trust the code at all.
So before the kernel loads a program,
it has to be written in this instruction
set and walk every possible path
through it and prove that the thing
will terminate and only touches the
memory that it was actually given.
And if it fails the proof, then
the program doesn't actually load.
And then you pass it an unrestricted
code and safely run in the kernel space.
And so that's the whole trick.
You're converting this into a proof.
And so then Daniel Borkman comes on
the scene and he's a developer with
experience with writing kernel code,
and he gets excited about the j-
idea, and together they develop eBPF.
And they call it eBPF because it's
a technology in the kernel and
previously there was already BPF,
which is just without the extended bit.
And they call it eBPF because of
the similarity, and the need also
came from somewhat different places.
They weren't just thinking about BPF,
BB- BPP- BPF at first, and BPF is also
a specific machine that's not nearly
powerful enough to do what they needed.
But that's where the name comes from
And once it all shipped, the economics
flipped and it starts becoming effective.
So you can compile a program, load it
into a running machine, and it's live.
And so what used to take years
now take just a few days.
And the first proof of scale was an
L4 load balancer from Facebook and
roughly fifty nanoseconds per packet
with ten times faster than IPVS.
And so that project was known as
Katran, and they open source it.
But there is a catch.
Writing eBPF at this point means
writing byte code and then arguing
with a verifier that rejects you
for reasons you don't understand.
So huge black box and realistically,
you really needed a kernel team.
And I just wanna keep this in mind because
I don't want one question you to be
asking is like, "Why are you talking to
me about a technology that is so old?"
Because the reality is it took quite a
while for things to catch up, to mature
to the point where they are today, where
a bunch of cool companies can be doing
things that we see happening today.
And so in 2015 Brendan Gregg,
whose quote we saw earlier and
others also start realize that
there are a ton of uses for eBPF.
It came from the networking
world that we talked about.
But Brendan Gregg is also a performance
guy, and he was working on observability
at Net- Netflix at the time.
And he realized that with this
programmability at the kernel, you
can also do a lot of other things.
So he leads the development of
platforms like bcc and bpftrace
which we will see later.
And it also made it easy to
write eBPF code and come with a
ton of ready-made eBPF tools for
anyone who wants to use them.
So I really like this comic quite
a bit just because it explains
pretty simply what things were
like before and after eBPF.
So before eBPF, if I'm a user-mode
programmer and I need some feature from
the kernel, I have to go to a kernel
programmer and tell them that I need it.
And that kernel programmer has to start
convincing the community that the feature
is needed, and that can take a long time.
And even when it finally lands, it's
not in the Ubuntu I happen to be using,
and so I might need to wait a few years
until I can upgrade and actually use it.
And that's pretty hard and
practically not even very realistic.
But with eBPF, the user-mode programmer
goes to an eBPF programmer which he
has or which he can maybe even be
himself, so it could even be simpler.
And within a few days or hours, he
already has what he needs, and he
doesn't even need to restart his software
So let's talk about some use
cases and why people use eBPF.
So we talked a little bit about networking
and where it c-- and that's kinda where
it came from, and we'll also talk about
security and observability as well.
Let's kinda summarize too and talk
more about networking to start us off.
In the networking world, here's
a very simple code example and
you can do a packet filtering.
So here's some static code that
just filters a certain point.
Obviously, it's code, so that's
the power that this thing
gives me over prior filtering.
Like what you just had with IP tables,
for example, is that I can filter whatever
I want, any logic I can write in code,
and I can do load balancing, I can simply
measure how much different applications
use network access, et cetera.
Excuse me.
And for example for anyone here who has
Android and not some other operating
system, can open the settings for a
given app and see how much network it's
using, and that's computed using eBPF.
Because before that, they had a
kernel module Android wrote, and they
replaced it with eBPF because it's more
efficient and safer for other reasons.
So now let's talk about eBPF for security.
In the security world
you can place probes.
Probe is the name that we give to
this code we run as an event listener,
and I can put one on the open
function, for example, and see all
file access in an operating system.
And I can see the processes running,
when they stop, and for what reason.
And I can implement a
firewall and a lot more.
And eBPF for observability.
So in the observability world,
which is where I more come from,
you can do a lot of cool things.
For example, I can measure
the latency of things.
I can take disk write, which is used
to write a file write to a file,
and I can measure how long it takes.
Okay, so I put two probes and on entry
and exit, and I can simply measure
how much time has passed between them.
I can also get access to all the
communication on a machine and
use that for a lot of things.
To understand, for example, how long
it takes for traffic to arrive and
leave, and also to find bad traffic.
For example, if I see an HTTP 400 on
a certain API, I can understand that
there's an error here, and that maybe I
need to handle that in my application.
I can also do profiling, so I can
instrument the code at all sorts
of points and understand where
it's spending most of the time.
And as I said, there's also a ton
of other examples when I show you
this latency monitor example from
the previous slide maybe to a
developer, they might ask hang on.
I write code.
I can measure how long it
takes me to write to a file.
Why do I need this nonsense?"
And the thing is, there are
several advantages here.
Say I have code in production
and I want to measure how long
it takes to write to a file.
With eBPF, I don't even need to
ship a new version of that code.
I run the measurement
directly from the kernel.
I don't even need to restart the software.
So I get full coverage of all writes
to all files at once, and I don't need
to add another piece of instrumentation
and ship a new version every time.
It's usually faster and easier, right?
And obviously, I can also measure
a lot of things that are internal
kernel functionality, which in my
own code, I obviously can't do.
There's also a certain
downside, okay, missing context.
For example, if I want to measure how
long it takes to write to a file, and
on every write understand the value
of some variable I have in my code,
that's a little harder with eBPF.
Possible, but harder.
Oops.
So let's also talk about
some use cases for eBPF.
There are really much more than
this and I really recommend you
look when you leave here at what you
already know and what could help you.
So there are some stable products
that have been around for a
long time, like Android, as I
mentioned, that are gradually
introducing eBPF where it can help.
And there are also new companies
like GroundCover that are built
on eBPF from the ground up, and
there are more appearing over
time as this technology matures
So how does eBPF work?
This is the most interesting part in
my view, and it's a bit more technical
and harder, but also not super long.
So we'll touch on a few points here.
And this is based on slides that
Brendan Gregg presented a while back.
And if it interests you,
it's a fantastic talk.
I recommend looking at it afterwards.
It's called eBPF Internals.
Yeah, enjoy that talk.
Go look it up.
So let's talk about eBPF and how
it works, and let's start with
eBPF probes for this example
So there's a kernel function called
do_nanosleep that's called every
time a program tries to sleep,
and that's an interesting place.
And my probe is pretty simple.
Every time there's a do_nanosleep, it
writes which processes went to sleep, and
it uses a BPF helper, and helpers are the
functions that can call from eBPF co-code.
And this helper is called
bpf_get_current_pid_tgid
to get the process ID.
And so then I compile this
thing to a target that is BPF,
and that's the instruction set.
And I don't compile it to x86,
even though in the example we're
discussing it'll run on that processor.
Instead, I compile it to BPF.
And what does that look like?
My helper has a number 14, and
every helper has a number, and
every instruction I compile into
a byte sequence into byte code.
And this is what BPF byte code
looks like, and this is the object
file that I compiled, for example.
A jump to BPF helper is an instruction
whose sequence number is zero eighty-five,
and my helper number is fourteen.
So right inside the code, we can
see a byte sequence of zero by
eighty-five, some zeros, and fourteen.
And essentially all my
code is in this byte code.
And this code is going to run inside
the kernel, which is pretty dangerous
if you stop and think about it for
a second, because what I'm telling
you is that from a user mode I
can write whatever code I want and
it's gonna get stuck in the kernel.
And the kernel did a ton of work to secure
this and make sure it didn't get stuck.
So there's a kernel component called
the verifier that goes over the eBPF
code and makes sure it doesn't do
anything we don't want it to do.
So its job is to impose
all kinds of restrictions.
It limits the amount of
memory code my code can use.
It limits the number of instructions
that I can run, so I don't run an
infinite loop and hang the kernel.
It doesn't allow my kernel to sleep,
plus many other restrictions as well.
So to verify all these things, it goes
over my code and keeps a ton of states,
and it walks every flow in the code.
So say I have some variable in the
code called X, and in my code I
check if X is greater than three.
So now I've just created a branch,
and the kernel verifier walks this
flow on one hand if X is greater than
three, and on the other hand if it's
less than or equal to three, and it
continues down both flows, running
like that all the way to the end.
And then it verifies that in
every flow my code exists, that
it doesn't do anything stupid.
So in this way, the verifier is really the
part that creates the trust, and it's what
converts the question from, "Do we trust
this code?" to, "We trust this proof."
So now that the kernel has this code and
that it is approved for execution and it
needs it to run it, how does it do that?
There's that do_nanosleep function in
the kernel, and this is its disassembly.
The code that's actually in the
kernel, and you can see the first
instruction here is the call, and it's
essentially a jump into eBPF code.
So what does that kernel do?
It literally goes to its own
code and modifies it at runtime.
It adds a call instruction to what's
called a trampoline meaning that
the moment that the do_nanosleep is
called, the kernel will execute the
function, jump into my code, and
at the end of my code it jumps back
to the beginning of do_nanosleep.
And so the function we're looking or
hooking runs as if it were never there.
And so now that my code is running BPF
code, not 686 like we see here we now
wanna ask, how does the kernel do it?
Like, how exactly Does it do it?
How, it does it basically
exactly like JavaScript does.
So JIT compiling, it compiles the
code from BBPF just in time at
runtime as follows, and it goes
over the instructions one by one.
And in our example, it reaches the
hypercall function or instruction and
it sees that this instruction says,
"I'll translate this from BBPF to 686.
And instead of 0 by 85, I'll put 0E8 in
there," which is equivalent jump in x86.
And the number 14 translates it
into the real address inside the
kernel of the imment- implementation
of the helper that I'm running.
So it does that one by one for
all the instructions until it's
done compiling everything, and
then my code effectively runs.
Virtually, yes, but as if it had
been 686 code from the start,
and it's a very efficient way to
actual- execute and virtualize code
Okay, so how has BPF looked over
time and eBPF looked over time?
So in '91 we had CBPF, which was
good mainly for packet capturing
with tcdump, tcpdump, and Wireshark.
And then in 2014, eBPF is ready and
we have a full virtual machine inside
the kernel and I can probe what I
want or almost everything what I want.
For example, I can't put a probe
on the verifier's implementation
in the kernel and that's a problem
But then in 2019, they
add critical things.
So in 2019, I can write eBPF code
with loops in it, and you can
imagine previously try writing
code without loops in it good luck.
They are also, for example, able
to raise the instruction limit
from four thousand to a million,
and they add what's called CRE.
So that's code that ran on a kernel
version that can run on other versions.
And this processing really continues
in 25 as well as they added the
ability from EB- from eBPF to
hook into the operating system
scheduling mechanisms and essentially
decide which processes will run.
So let's talk about scripting.
How do we use eBPF?
At the easy end, you use platforms
that have eBPF in them, and at the
hard end, which we won't talk about
today, you write eBPF code yourself.
In the middle, you can use either
ready-made tools, like WriteBPF
in a scripted form or bcc tools.
And bcc is a platform with tons and
tons of tools, and even more than that,
what's shown here, for example this is
a fairly old screenshot that it has tons
of tools that I think everyone could use.
For example, you can see which processes
died because they all ran out of
memory, which processes exist, and
everything that runs from bash, all TCP
connections, and many more examples.
So these are all the tools that you
can see here that you might wanna use.
So let's actually go into demo
and see a bit of scr- tracing and
scripting, excuse me, with bpftrace.
So again, thank you,
Ori, for these examples.
Just wanna highlight them here.
So this first demo shows an example
where we see a short script that we
run from the command line, and it
simply shows us all the files that
are being opened on operating system.
So basically what's being run here
is bpftrace -e, meaning that I'm
running it from the command line.
I put a tracepoint on a syscall
called openat which happens in the
kernel every time a file is opened.
And I simply print the process ID and
the name and the file that was opened
And all I need to know for this is
that the open function oh, there we go.
It's… There we go.
Just pr- press Enter.
That I want to put the probe on
and its argument that holds the
name of the file that's about to
be opened, in this case, filename.
Okay, so we saw here in real time
all the files being opened on the
operating system, and for example
there's Go that opened here, and it
looks like it's probably compiling.
And let's look at this second example.
So we're decrypting TLS traffic
with an up probe in this example.
We see a server called server
and we can see its process ID,
and it communicates encrypted, so
we're about to see the traffic.
And so let's say I wanna know a bit
about this process and what it does.
What I can then do is I can print its maps
file which will show me all the shared
objects and all the loaded libraries
And then I see libssl, which is loaded,
meaning it'll probably speak encrypted.
And if I try to see the traffic with
tcdump, for example, I see that it won't
succeed, and I can see that roughly once
a second there's some traffic, and it's
encrypted, so I don't see the content.
So I can see the content with bpff trace.
And I run it again with -e from the
command line, and I'm going to attach an
upprobe which is a user mode probe because
this is a library and not a kernel code,
on the SSL write function, which receives
the buffer and its length in unencrypted,
encrypts it, and sends the encrypted data.
So I'll put this probe on, filter
it so it only runs when the command
is running its server, and that way
I can simply print the unencrypted
data every time that it is sent
So here we are attaching the probe,
and we can see the unencrypted.
Amazing Okay, so now let's talk
about the third example, which is
also the most complicated which is
tracking writes to one specific file.
So I'm gonna show monitoring writes
to that specific file, and the
way that I wanna do that is let's
say I want to monitor writes to
a file called reverse SIM 2025.
So you can put a probe on the
write syscall and print the
process ID and what it wrote.
But there is a problem with that,
and the problem is that it just will
print me everything written to the
file, and I wanna know which file.
So the write syscall doesn't get you a
file name, it gets a file descriptor,
and that's exactly how you work with it.
And to get the file descriptor, you first
have to open the file, so I actually
need to put another probe on open which
we've already seen, and I will… Right
here we have seen, and I will then
filter this probe to run only when
my argument is the file name matching
the actual file that I care about.
And I'll save that particular
invocation of open.
And why will I do this?
Because on the way out of open,
I get the file descriptor.
So I need a third probe, okay, so that I
can save it into a map in kernel memory
that this invocation of open interests me.
And then on the exit from open,
if it was an open on a file that
I care about, I'm gonna save the
file descriptor in a second map.
So I have the FDS map, which maps
from the process ID, To the relevant
file descriptor that now corresponds
only to the file I care about.
And I'll filter the probe I already
wrote on the write syscall to
fire only when the file descriptor
matches the file that I care about.
And when I run this thing
the whole flow will happen.
We'll say a process writes to the file.
It will then call open, and
it'll get a file descriptor.
You track all of that, and the moment
it writes to the file, my probe on write
sees it and prints the actual data for us.
So here we attach three probes at this
time, and is a little bit more complicated
with state between them, but the probes
really communicate with each other, and
the moment I write to the file, we see it
So thank you so much.
I hope that was interesting.
And as I said, what I really want
you to walk out of this talk with is
an understanding that eBPF is super
cool and super powerful technology
that you can use for a ton of things.
And I think everyone here can find
examples where it will help them.
And I really recommend
looking into what's out there.
For example, all of the tools
in BCC, there are tons, and
also, exploring groundcover.
Thank you so much for your time.